We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
Did you know that those who eat spicy
foods regularly tend to live longer?
Here’s our first story.
Most people could name
four of the basic tastes:
sweet, sour, salty, and bitter.
The rare foodie may
be able to nail umami,
but what about “the forgotten
ﬂavour sense,” spicy?
This seeming neglect is somewhat
surprising given that hot peppers
are one of the world's
most widely-used spices.
In fact, as many as one
in four people on the planet
currently eat chilies on a daily
basis, raising the question,
“Why is spicy
food so popular?”
Why do some like it hot, enjoying
what is, at ﬁrst glance,
an irritating, and potentially
painful mouth sensation?
According to one
popular suggestion,
it is the endorphin hit,
the release of your natural
morphine-like
painkiller chemicals
from your brain.
You hear this a lot in the popular
press, but we still don’t have
any convincing evidence
to support it.
Another suggestion is that
we learned to use it
for its antimicrobial properties
before the age of refrigeration,
given that spicy food tends
to be preferred by cultures
living in warmer climates,
and for that matter,
maybe it makes us sweat and thereby
ultimately helps cool us down.
Then again, maybe it’s just
because people just like the taste.
Preference for spicy foods does
seem to run in families.
Based on twin studies comparing
the preferences of identical
to fraternal twins, genetic
factors may account
for up to half of the variation,
similar to the heritability
of sweet and sour preferences.
It may also be hormonal.
Researchers in France noted
that particularly males
liked spicy food
and wondered if it was
a testosterone thing.
So, they took a group
of more than 100 men
and gave them a plate
of mashed potatoes
and asked them to Tabasco
the potatoes to taste,
after taking saliva samples
to measure their testosterone levels.
And what do you know, men
who had higher testosterone
added more hot sauce.
That may help explain
this study that found
a correlation between
hot chili pepper consumption
and muscle strength
in adult males.
As an aside, when I was looking
at the testosterone literature,
I ran across this study
that showed young men experience
an acute decrease in blood
testosterone levels
after chugging sugar water
or whey protein powder:
12- to 18-year-olds were randomized
to a few scoops of protein power
or about two cans of soda worth
of sugar, and within 20 minutes
saw a significant drop
in testosterone levels
compared to a sugar-free,
protein-free control.
This is consistent with lower
testosterone levels
found in people on high
protein, low carb diets.
Anyway, what does
the consumption
of hot spicy foods
do to our lifespan?
Well, a massive study of a half
million men and women in China
found that those regularly
eating spicy foods
had an associated 14 percent
reduction in total mortality,
meaning the risk
of premature death.
That could translate into about
an extra year onto your lifespan,
if it is cause and effect.
Those of you who
follow my work know
there are two main potential
issues with observational studies:
reverse causality
and confounding factors.
In other words,
instead of spicy foods
leading to less disease,
maybe disease is leading
to less spicy food, with sick
people eating blander diets.
However, the apparent
benefit remained
even after excluding
sick folks,
or those who were just
about to croak.
And so, reverse causality
doesn’t seem to explain it,
though hey, people who eat
spicy food probably drink more,
and what do they
drink in China?
Green tea; so, maybe
that’s what going on?
It would be nice
to replicate this
in a non-green tea drinking
country or even a country
that drinks terrible stuff,
like the United States.
And yet same thing, a 13 percent
risk reduction in premature death.
And the protective
association remained
even after controlling for
Mexican-American ethnicity.
As I detailed before, they have
a longevity advantage,
presumably because
they eat so many beans.
Same thing was found
in Italy, this time
a 23 percent lower
all-cause mortality.
That’d be like two
extra years of life.
The authors conclude
that minor dietary changes,
such as just adding chilies
to one’s usual diet,
could be a valuable measure
for improving health.
There have been four
studies done overall,
including this one in Iran,
that all found the same thing:
significantly lower risk
of premature death.
In fact, black or chili pepper
consumption was associated
with about the same
lifespan extension as turmeric,
even at just like
a pinch a day.
And, those that did both
seemed to do even better,
which is consistent with the ability
of a black pepper compound
to boost the bioavailability
of the turmeric compound curcumin.
I’ve got about 50 videos on why
turmeric is so good for you,
but why might chili peppers
extend your life?
We’ll find out, next.
Four out of four studies
on spicy food and mortality
found a significant decrease
in the risk of premature death.
The intake of sweet peppers
also seemed to help,
but to a lesser extent;
so, there may be some benefit
to the spicy capsaicin
compound itself.
I have a whole section on chili
peppers in my Fat Burners chapter
in How Not to Diet:
how cayenne pepper can counteract
the metabolic slowing
that accompanies weight loss
and accelerate
fat burning as a bonus.
So, maybe the weight loss benefits
account for the mortality benefits?
Apparently not, since there was
a mortality risk reduction
with chili pepper
consumption
even after controlling
for body mass index.
Maybe the spice was used
as a replacement for salt?
Anything that reduces sodium
intake could improve longevity,
as excess salt consumption
is the deadliest dietary risk factor,
the worst thing
about the human diet,
wiping out millions
of people every year.
Not only could you use
the spice to replace salt,
the spicy compound
actually makes things
taste saltier than
they actually are.
Sprinkling on some
red pepper powder
can increase your salt
taste sensitivity;
so, you can achieve the same
salty taste with less salt.
You can put people in a PET
scanner and pick up differences
in their secondary taste cortex,
the part of your brain
associated with pleasure
signaling to salty foods.
So, you can use hot peppers
to hack your brain for your health.
And indeed, those with
a high spice preference
had lower salt intake
and better blood pressures,
and this again appears
to be independent
of the anti-obesity benefit
of hot pepper consumption,
though the lower risk
of developing high blood pressure
among those with higher
hot pepper intake
was also independent
of sodium intake;
so, there may be some other
benefit pathways as well
like maybe it also helps your
kidneys excrete more salt too,
though the evidence
to support this was derived
from studies on mice;
so, who knows.
However it works, eating
spicy foods or adding
supplemental spicy flavor
to food by like
sprinkling on cayenne
pepper or hot sauce
represents a novel
lifestyle intervention
that can reduce both salt
intake and blood pressure.
Here are some examples
of no-salt added hot sauces.
Even regular tabasco
is pretty low in sodium,
though only
the original flavor.
Some of their other
spin-off flavors like
buffalo/habanero/chipotle
have 5 times more.
Now, just because all studies
on spicy food and mortality to date
suggest hot peppers
may help you live longer
doesn’t mean you can go out
and eat a ghost pepper,
designated the Guinness book’s
hottest pepper in the world in 2007.
Some varieties of habanero can be
50 times as hot as jalapenos.
To get to ghost
peppers, though,
you have to switch over
to millions of units.
The ghost pepper beat out
the habanero in 2007,
which itself got out shadowed
by the Trinidad Scorpion in 2011,
and then 2013, burning as the
reigning champ, the Carolina Reaper.
The only thing hotter than
the reaper is pure pepper spray,
which can lead to such violent
coughing you can rupture a lung.
Pepper spray in the eye
only seems to be a problem
if you can’t wash it out.
The best thing you can do
if you’re trying to help someone
sprayed in the face
is try to calm them down,
make sure they’re breathing ok,
remove their contact lenses
as soon as possible,
and then, abundantly irrigate
their eyes to wash
out the chemical.
Really abundantly, as in washing
their eyes with water or saline
for a full 10-20 minutes,
which is a long time
to be washing your eye out.
Again, after contact lenses
have been removed,
or even better not
worn to an event
where you might be pepper
sprayed in the first place.
Even just ambient exposure
to pepper gas can cause
dry eye symptoms
that last for weeks,
even if you’re not
sprayed directly.
It’s ironic that the
Chemical Weapons Convention
prohibits the use of these riot
control agents during warfare;
yet, they are routinely used
to quell civilian protest.
The most serious eye injuries
though, are trauma
from fired projectiles
like pepper balls,
leading to the suggestion
that protestors wear
ballistic eye protection,
recommending that medical centers
proactively reach out to protest
leaders and participants
regarding appropriate
safety precautions.
In terms of what you can
do for pepper spray irritation
on your skin, there
are anecdotal reports
that baby shampoo is helpful.
However, as yet, there have been
no published scientific studies
that demonstrate their
effectiveness until...now.
“Baby Shampoo to Relieve
the Discomfort
of Tear Gas and Pepper
Spray Exposure:
A Randomized Controlled Trial.”
Police recruits received a burst
of pepper spray to the face,
then were randomized
to washing off with water
or water along with some Johnson
& Johnson baby shampoo and…
it didn’t work at all.
How about using Maalox,
or a numbing lidocaine
gel, or milk?
Nothing beat out
plain old water.
Copious water decontamination
is the preferred method
of pain control after topical
pepper spray exposure.
Anyways, that was quite
the tangent.
Bottomline, should we all
begin taking tablets of capsaicin
and dousing our food
with hot sauce?
If you like hot sauce, go for it,
but I don’t think we should start
taking supplements
until we have randomized,
controlled trials proving benefit.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.